<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>A Shakespeherian Rag</title>
    <description>A blog about whatever piques my (short-lived) interest
</description>
    <link>http://yourdomain.com/</link>
    <atom:link href="http://yourdomain.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Tue, 10 Feb 2015 18:14:23 -0500</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 10 Feb 2015 18:14:23 -0500</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v2.5.3</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>The Modest Woman</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;I found myself more or less locked in today: classes cancelled, library closed, and too much snow on the ground. I’ve been working through Joyce’s &lt;em&gt;Ulysses&lt;/em&gt; lately with more serious intent, and I decided to dive into some of the criticism leveled against the work when it  debuted in serial in &lt;em&gt;The Little Review&lt;/em&gt;, a journal frequently contributed to by Pound and his coterie. Of particular note (so says Wikipedia) was an essay written by the Dada artist Else von Freytag-Loringhoven titled “The Modest Woman.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Briefly, it appears that she wrote the essay (for vol. 7 no. 2 of &lt;em&gt;The Little Review&lt;/em&gt;) in response to a letter (also entitled “The Modest Woman”) that the magazine printed in the previous issue. In the letter, Ms. Helen Bishop Dennis of Boston bemoaned what she viewed as the embrace of “obscenity” in &lt;em&gt;Ulysses&lt;/em&gt; by the staff of &lt;em&gt;The Little Review&lt;/em&gt;, claiming to come from a place less prude than prudent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Freytag-Loringhoven responded by drawing parallels between true &lt;em&gt;artists&lt;/em&gt; and aristocrats (a topic certainly near and dear to the author-baroness). While the “little people” of Europe, in her estimation, rightly deferred to the elegance of the artist-aristocracy, Americans (ah, stereotypes; thank you Ms. Helen Bishop Dennis) had no such tradition of rigid and formal social stratification and consequently lacked the grace to simply be quiet in the face of art that they didn’t understand. I also rather like (for obvious reasons) Freytag-Loringhoven’s characterization of &lt;em&gt;the artist&lt;/em&gt; as an engineer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I found the text for both (after no small labor) through the Modernist Journals Project out of Brown University and the University of Tulsa. Vol. 7 no. 1 can be found &lt;a href=&quot;http://library.brown.edu/pdfs/1299775791781253.pdf&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; and vol. 7 no. 2 can be found &lt;a href=&quot;http://library.brown.edu/pdfs/1299776600843754.pdf&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I couldn’t find plaintext versions of either on the web, so I’m leaving the following here for posterity.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;the-modest-woman&quot;&gt;The Modest Woman&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Helen Bishop Dennis, Boston&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I notice that the first letter under the Reader Critic in your April issue
suggests that “after all these months James Joyce might be accepted, obscenity
and all, for … only a few read him, and those few not just
the kind to have their whole moral natures overthrown by frankness about
natural functions.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The mistake you people make is in thinking that we “prudes” who
don’t like Joyce are concerned with morals. Morality has nothing to do
with it. Does morality have anything to do with the average person’s
desire for privacy concerning the “natural functions”? Not at all; it
is delicacy, lack of vulgarity. I do not think we need to apologize for
this delicacy and lack of vulgarity, even to your superior beings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is a certain form of mental unbalance—about the lowest form—
that takes delight in concentration on the “natural functions… All attendants
in insane asylums are familiar with it. Does James Joyce belong
to those so affected? Do “the few who read him” belong? If not, and
Joyce and his readers are to be considered fairly sane, would he—and
they—be willing to perform their “natural functions” in public? If not,
why take out a desire for dabbling in filth, in writing in public?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The only cure for the nausea he causes is the thought that “only a few
read him.” I think the Little Review has become a disgustingly artificial
and affected publication. You started out to be sincere, unconventional, to
refuse to pander to commercialism, etc.: a wonderfully courageous and
admirable ambition. But you are a great disappointment to those  of us
who hoped great things for you. You are like a crowd of precocious,
“smarty cat,” over-wise children, showing off. I know of no one who
has anything for you now but pity, mingled with contempt and disappointment—and
this from people who were once your friends and admirers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;editor: Yes, I think you must be right. I once knew a woman so modest that
she didn’t wear underwear: she couldn’t stand its being seen in the wash.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;the-modest-woman-1&quot;&gt;The Modest Woman&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Else von Freytag-Loringhoven&lt;/em&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Artists are aristocrats.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Artists who call themselves artists—not aristocrats—are plain working
people, mixing up art with craft, in vulgar untrained brain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Who wants us to hide our joys (Joyce?)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If I can eat I can eliminate—it is logic—it is why I eat! My
machinery is built that way. Yours also—though you do not like to
think of—mention it—because you are not aristocrat.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Your skirts are too long—out of “modesty,” not decoration—when
you lift them you do not do it elegantly—proudly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why should I—proud engineer—be ashamed of my machinery—part of it? &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Is there any engineer of steel machinery who is? unless he runs
ramshackle one?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The stronger she works—the prouder he is!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Has he no right to talk shop? He, not you! for you are no engineer!
Helpless victim—pulled over gravel—dust—by that indecent
machine—your body—over life’s glorious wilderness—not seeing
landscape! Joyce is engineer! one of boldest—most adventurous—
globetrotter—! to talk shop is his sacred business—we want him to
—to love engine that carries him through flashing glades to his grave
—his glorious estate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If I can write—talk—about dinner—pleasure of my palate—as
artist or as aristocrat—with my ease of manner—can afford also to
mention my ecstasies in toilet room!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you can not—you are invited to silence—by all means!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If your ears are too vulgar—put white cotton into—in tufts—
bunches! fitting decoration! You did that—already—but why have
you to show it to the world at large? afflicted people should stay
home—with family—friends. You are immodest—because you are
not healthy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Toilets are made for swift cleanliness—not modesty!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;America’s comfort:—sanitation—outside machinery—has made
American forget own machinery—body! He thinks of himself less
than of what should be his servant—steel machinery.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He has mixed things! For: he has no poise—no tradition. Parvenu—ashamed of his hide—as he well might.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Slips behind smoothness—smugness—sanitation—cleanliness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ah! now he is “personality”—dressed up—sorry—sanitary lout—just from barber—smelling from barber.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That is American! it is truly disgusting to imagine him in any “physical functions”—eating not excluded.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Eats stupidly also.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Has reason to hide—feels that—and :—because newly rich—in vast
acquisition—feels also he has something to say to everything—everybody—as did in war—to ridicule.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Smart aleck—countrylout—in Sunday attire—strutting!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yawning—all teeth—into space—sipping his coffee with thunder noise—elbow on table—little finger outspread stiffly—he knows how to behave in society!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why—America—can you not be modest? stay back—attentive—as wellbred child? You have so much to learn—just out of bushes!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But—you are no wellbred child—you are noisy—nosey—bad-mannered—assumptive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my opinion—I have sharp eyes—you are no child of nature—you are changeling!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You forget, madame—that we are the masters—go by our rules.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Goethe was grandly obscene—what do you know about it? Flaubert—Swift—Rabelais—Arabian
Nights—Bible if you please! only
difference—Bible is without humour—great stupidity! So: how
dare you strut—step out—show yourself with your cotton-tuft in ear?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Europe—when inferiors do not understand superiors—they retire
modestly—mayhap baffled—but in good manner. By that fact
—that they do not understand—-they know their place. They are
not invited—of class inferior—the dance is not theirs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They can not judge—for: they lack real manners—education—class.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If they are desirous of judging—sometime—they must think—study—rise—slowly! So society is made—in Europe—slowly—! so: culture—so: aristocratic public.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In such public—we dance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That attitude of the learner—the inferior—you should feel in regard
to James Joyce.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That you do not—shows you have less inherent culture than European
washer-lady.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here—madame—every bank clerk meddles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ancient Romans had proverb—one of few great principals of
world-structure—culture: &lt;em&gt;Quod licit Jovi, non licit Bovi&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To show hidden beauty of things—there are no limitations! Only
artist can do that—that is his holy office. Stronger—braver he is—more he will explore into depths.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;His eye—ear—-finger—nose—tongue—are as keen as yours dull.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Without him—without his help—you would become less than dog—cow—worm. &lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 10 Feb 2015 12:17:45 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>http://yourdomain.com/joyce/2015/02/10/the-modest-woman.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://yourdomain.com/joyce/2015/02/10/the-modest-woman.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>joyce</category>
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
